<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE riscos-prm PUBLIC "-//Gerph//DTD PRM documentation 1.02//EN"
                            "http://www.movspclr.co.uk/dtd/102/prm.dtd">

<riscos-prm>
<chapter title="DCI Statistics">
<section title="Introduction">

<p>The maintenance of statistics such as "packets transmitted" for a network
interface can greatly assist the system administrator (or user) in a variety
of circumstances.
</p>

<p>Traditionally, support for such statistics gathering has been irregular and
generally limited to direct screen printing.  This specification provides a
more controlled method of presenting statistics to the user, and permits a
single generic display program to cope with all compliant modules.
</p>

<p>The following characterise the intentions of this interface specification:
</p>

<p>
<list>
    <item><p><strong>Plus points</strong></p>
        <p>
        <list>
            <item>Simplicity of implementation</item>
            <item>Single generic statistics display program</item>
            <item>No essential central information that needs frequent updating</item>
            <item>Information is for presentation to humans primarily</item>
            <item>Atomic operations without any latching mechanisms</item>
            <item>Well-behaved with multiple gatherers</item>
            <item>Well-behaved if a supplier unexpectedly disappears</item>
            <item>Virtually stateless communication</item>
        </list>
        </p>
    </item>
    <item><p><strong>Minus points</strong></p>
        <p>
        <list>
            <item>Not re-entrant - callbacks or user mode code only</item>
            <item>Restrictive string model</item>
            <item>Polled interface, rather than event driven</item>
            <item>Only simple flat structure to statistics</item>
            <item>Only really suitable for human display</item>
        </list>
        </p>
    </item>
</list>
</p>

</section>


<section title='Technical Details'>

<subsection title="Basics of operation">

<p>A piece of software that wishes to offer statistics is termed a "supplier".
A piece of software that obtains statistics from a supplier and presents them
to the user is termed a "gatherer", and the operation it performs is often
referred to as "enumerating the statistics".  There are typically more
suppliers than gatherers in a system.
</p>

<p>As part of its normal operations, a supplier maintains a set of statistics.
A gatherer, typically upon user invocation, enumerates the available
suppliers, enumerates the statistics supplied by each supplier and then
presents this information to the user.  More dynamic presentation is also
possible.  A supplier is passive (other than its normal operations), whilst
the gatherer actively seeks out the information to be presented.
</p>

<p>The first stage of enumeration (determining what suppliers are present) is
performed with a service call (<reference type='service' name='StatisticEnumerate'/>),
and the second stage (determining what
statistics are available and their values) is performed through a SWI whose
SWI number is obtained during the first stage of enumeration
(<reference type='swi' name='StatisticsProvider_Statistics'/>).  This SWI
number is used for all stages of operation apart from enumeration itself.
</p>

<p>Each statistic has a number of different pieces of information associated
with it, forming its description, and a value.  The description provides the
necessary information to access and manipulate the value, including the
number of bytes of storage required for the value, it's type, format and
desired presentation.  The data types supported are boolean, integer and
string.  An unused data type also provides for padding.
</p>

<p>Descriptions and statistics are read in ranges from a lower statistic number
to an upper statistic number, inclusive.  The first statistic of any supplier
is zero.  The highest statistic number of a supplier is obtained when the SWI
number for a supplier is obtained.  A range is always processed atomically by
the supplier, ensuring consistent values and presentation to a gatherer when so
required.  A supplier indicates the volatility of its statistics and
typically attempts to group statistics into ranges of the same volatility.
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Enumerating suppliers">
<p>The list of available suppliers is determined with a single service
call, <reference type='service' name='StatisticEnumerate'/>.</p>

<p>
On receiving this service, each supplier allocates a small structure from the RMA,
initializes it and links it into the linked list whose head is pointed to by R0.
Whether the supplier adds an entry at the head or tail of the list does not matter,
although it is recommended that the entries be added to the head for simplicity.  If a
gatherer requires any specific order, then it should explicitly sort the
suppliers list itself.  A gatherer should not cache SWI values across
invocations of suppliers, as a module might choose a dynamic SWI numbering
scheme if it offers multiple effective suppliers.
</p>

<category title='Statistics Provider Structure'>
<p>In C, this structure is defined as follows:
</p>

<p>
<extended-example type='c'>
typedef struct spctl
{
    struct spctl       *next;           /* Next structure in list */
    unsigned int        i_version;      /* Interface version */
    unsigned long       features;       /* Combination of SF_ values */
    unsigned int        swinumber;      /* The SWI SA_DESCRIBE/SA_READ use */
    unsigned int        max_stat;       /* Highest stat number (inclusive) */
    unsigned int        type;           /* Acorn assigned supplier type */
    unsigned int        s_version;      /* Supplier version */
    char               *module;         /* Module name (short one) */
    char               *title;          /* Title string - short */
    char               *description;    /* Descriptive string - long */
    unsigned char       reset[8];       /* Unique for each invocation */
} dci4_spctl;
</extended-example>
</p>

<p>
<offset-table>
    <offset number='0' name='next'>This field is used to construct the linked list of
suppliers for the enumeration operation.  A value of zero indicates the end
of the list.</offset>

    <offset number='4' name='i_version'>The DCI4 Statistic Interface version that the
supplier is implemented against.</offset>

    <offset number='8' name='features'>A bitset of flags defining optional aspects of a
supplier. No features are currently defined and the the value must be set to 0.</offset>

    <offset number='12' name='swinumber'>The SWI number through which all other communication
with the supplier is performed.</offset>

    <offset number='16' name='max_stat'>The highest statistic number, inclusive, that the
supplier provides.  This implies a supplier must always supply at least one
statistic.</offset>

    <offset number='20' name='type'><p>This field is available to provide some classification of
suppliers.  It is the only centrally administered resource in this
specification, and its use is optional.  The currently defined values are as
follows:</p>

        <p>
        <value-table>
            <value name='SPT_GENERAL_SUPPLIER' number='0'>Use this if no other suitable type</value>
            <value name='SPT_NETWORK_PROTOCOL' number='1'>A DCI4 protocol module</value>
            <value name='SPT_NETWORK_DRIVER' number='2'>A DCI4 device driver module</value>
            <value name='SPT_MBUF_MANAGER' number='3'>The DCI4 mbuf manager module</value>
        </value-table>
        </p>
    </offset>

    <offset number='24' name='s_version'>This is the version number of the supplier module
itself (as opposed to the version number of an interface it conforms to).  It
is provided for the convenience of the user.</offset>

    <offset number='28' name='module'>This is the supplier's module title (as opposed to its help string).</offset>

    <offset number='32' name='title'>This is a short descriptive string to identify the supplier to
the user.  The gatherer only contracts to print at least the first twenty
characters of this string.</offset>

    <offset number='36' name='description'>This is a longer description of the supplier that should
convey it's purpose to the user.  The gatherer only contracts to print at
least the first fifty characters of this string.</offset>

    <offset number='40' name='reset'>This 8 byte field is initialised with a unique value
each time the supplier is initialised.  It permits the gatherer to spot a
supplier that has just re-initialised.  The time and date at which the
supplier initialises are recommended values to write here.  The gatherer
performs an 8 byte equality test and otherwise assumes no further format
information about these bytes.</offset>
</offset-table>
</p>
</category>

<p>When a gatherer has finished interacting with a supplier, it should free the
allocated structures back into the RMA.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection title="Describing and obtaining statistics">

<p>Apart from the enumeration phase, all communication with a supplier is
performed through the single SWI number obtained during the enumeration
phase (described as <reference type='swi' name='StatisticsProvider_Statistics'/>).</p>

<p>SA_DESCRIBE (0) obtains descriptions of statistics, whilst SA_READ (1) obtains the
actual values of statistics.  It is necessary for first obtain the
description of a statistic before reading it, as the description is the only
way the gatherer can obtain the size of the statistic value and know how much
buffer space to allocate.
</p>

<p>In essence, both these actions enumerate information about a range of
statistics into the buffer supplied.  This is performed atomically, where
necessary, by the supplier.  In both cases, the operation starts from the
first statistic and proceeds in steps of one and stops once the last
statistic has been processed.  Output is placed into the buffer supplied.  If
this buffer is not big enough for the requested range of statistics, then
processing will stop when it is no longer possible to write all the necessary
information for a statistic (i.e. if the buffer supplied is not big enough, the
number of unused bytes will be less than the size of a statistic
description).  Return values of the number of statistics processed and the
number of bytes of the buffer used are returned.  The buffer must be word
aligned in memory.
</p>


<category title='Statistic Description Structure'>
<p>Each statistic is described with a fixed sized buffer, described in C as follows:</p>

<p>
<extended-example type='c'>
typedef struct stdesc
{
    unsigned int            type;           /* ST_ series */
    unsigned int            format;         /* SxF_ series */
    unsigned int            presentation;   /* SxP_ series */
    unsigned int            size;           /* Measured in bytes */
    unsigned int            volatility;     /* SV_ series */
    char                   *name;           /* String is static */
    unsigned int            name_tag;       /* See specification */
    unsigned int            spare;          /* Unused. Always zero */
} dci4_stdesc;
</extended-example>
</p>


<p>
    <offset-table>
        <offset number='0' name='type'><p>This defines the type of statistic.  Possible values are:</p>
             <p>
             <value-table>
             <value name='ST_UNUSED' number='0'>
                <p>ST_UNUSED is used by a supplier to reserve a statistic number.  Such a
                statistic always has a value occupying zero bytes, and hence can always be
                enumerated, no matter how many bytes are left in the called supplied buffer.
                A statistic with a type of ST_UNUSED should always be skipped over when
                printing and enumerating - none of the fields beyond the type and size fields
                are valid for unused statistics.
                </p>
             </value>
             <value name='ST_BOOLEAN' number='1'>
                <p>ST_BOOLEAN values are single bit boolean values.  A variety of different
                presentation methods may be selected by the supplier in order to maximise
                coherence between the description and the presentation of a boolean value.
                Only the least significant bit of a boolean type has a defined value.
                </p>
             </value>
             <value name='ST_STRING' number='2'>
                <p>ST_STRING values are string values.  Currently, strings are defined using a
                zero byte as a terminator character {future versions may well introduce
                counted length strings as well).  A supplier is required to be able to place
                an upper length value on all strings so that sufficient space may be
                allocated within the caller supplied buffer for the SA_READ operation.
                </p>
             </value>
             <value name='ST_INTEGER8' number='3'>
                <p>ST_INTEGER8 is an 8-bit (byte) quantity.</p>
             </value>
             <value name='ST_INTEGER16' number='4'>
                <p>ST_INTEGER8 is an 16-bit (half-word) quantity.</p>
             </value>
             <value name='ST_INTEGER32' number='5'>
                <p>ST_INTEGER8 is an 32-bit (word) quantity.</p>
             </value>
             <value name='ST_INTEGER64' number='6'>
                <p>ST_INTEGER8 is an 64-bit (double-word) quantity.</p>
             </value>
             <value name='ST_ADDRESS' number='7'>
                <p>ST_ADDRESS values are addresses given in a protocol-specific format. A
                variety of different forms of address are possible. The presentation formats
                available for this type are presently undefined. This type of statistic is
                only supported by 1.01 of the DCI statistics format.
                </p>
             </value>
             <value name='ST_TIME' number='8'>
                <p>ST_TIME values are time values given in a variety of formats. The
                presentation methods presented allow for times to be specified in a number
                of ways. This type of statistic is only supported by 1.01 of the DCI
                statistics format.
                </p>
             </value>
            </value-table>
            </p>
        </offset>

        <offset number='4' name='format'><p>This field contains a value indicating the format of
            the value.  The range of values is specific to each type (all the integer
            types share a common set of formats and presentations for convenience).
            Depending upon the type in question, this value may be an enumeration, a
            bitset of flags or a combination of both (none of the currently defined
            formats mix enumeration and flag bitsets). See below for the meanings of the formats,
            </p></offset>

        <offset number='8' name='presentation'><p>This field dictates how the supplier would like
            the value to be presented.  A gatherer may choose to ignore this value, but
            only at the risk of presenting the user with incoherent information.
            See below for the meaning of the presentations.
            </p></offset>

        <offset number='12' name='size'>This is the number of bytes the statistic wishes reserved
in the buffer for an SA_READ operation.  It is always a multiple of four
bytes.  It is sometimes larger than the actual value necessary.</offset>

        <offset number='16' name='volatility'>
            <p>This field indicates how volatile a statistic is. The three possible values are:</p>

            <p>
            <value-table head-name='Name'>
             <value name='SV_STATIC' number='0'>Constant per invocation</value>
             <value name='SV_VARIABLE' number='1'>Unlikely to have changed in 5 minutes</value>
             <value name='SV_VOLATILE' number='2'>Can change very rapidly</value>
            </value-table>
            </p>
        </offset>

        <offset number='20' name='name'>This fields points at the name of the statistic.  It is a short
descriptive string that the gatherer contracts to display at least the first
twenty characters of.  The string itself is static, zero byte terminated and
contained with the supplier module.</offset>

        <offset number='24' name='name_tag'>
<p>This value, together with the information contained
in the dci4_spctl structure and a ISV/IHV supplied data file permit the
gatherer to obtain a description of a statistic.  The precise mechanism has
yet to be determined. Must be zero.
</p></offset>

        <offset number='28' name='spare'>This field is reserved for future use and must be zero.</offset>
</offset-table>
</p>

<p>
The format and presentation vary with the statistic types.
</p>
<p>
<value-table head-number='Statistic type' head-name='Name' head-value='Format and presentation'>
    <value number='0' name='ST_UNUSED'>There is no format or presentation defined for the ST_UNUSED type.</value>

    <value number='1' name='ST_BOOLEAN'>
        <p>Format:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='SBF_NORMAL' number='0'>The value supplied is 0 if boolean 'false' and any other value for boolean 'true'.</value>
                <value name='SBF_INVERTED' number='1'>The boolean state is inverted, 0 if boolean 'true' and any other value for boolean 'false'.</value>
        </value-table></p>
        <p>Presentation:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='SBP_ON_OFF' number='0'>The strings 'on' and 'off' will be used.</value>
                <value name='SBP_YES_NO' number='1'>The strings 'yes' and 'no' will be used.</value>
                <value name='SBP_TRUE_FALSE' number='2'>The strings 'true' and 'false' will be used.</value>
                <value name='SBP_ALWAYS_NEVER' number='3'>The strings 'always' and 'never' will be used.</value>
                <value name='SBP_ONE_ZERO' number='4'>The strings '1' and '0' will be used.</value>
        </value-table></p>
    </value>

    <value number='2' name='ST_STRING'>
        <p>Format:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='SSF_ZEROTERM' number='0'>This is the only defined format, indicating that the string is zero-terminated.</value>
        </value-table></p>
        <p>Presentation:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='SSP_LITERAL' number='0'>The string should be presented as supplied.</value>
        </value-table></p>
    </value>

    <value number='3-6' name='ST_INTEGER#'>
        <p>Format:</p>
        <p><bitfield-table>
                <bit name='SIF_UNSIGNED' number='0' state='set'>The value is unsigned</bit>
                <bit name='SIF_UNSIGNED' number='0' state='clear'>The value is signed</bit>
                <bit name='SIF_BIGENDIAN' number='1' state='set'>The value is supplied as big-endian</bit>
                <bit name='SIF_BIGENDIAN' number='1' state='clear'>The value is supplied as little-endian</bit>
                <bit number='2-31' state='reserved'/>
        </bitfield-table></p>
        <p>Presentation:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='SIP_HEXADECIMAL' number='0'>The value should be presented as a hexadecimal number.</value>
                <value name='SIP_DECIMAL' number='1'>The value should be presented as a decimal number.</value>
                <value name='SIP_DOTTED' number='2'>The value should be presented separating every octet with a '.' character. This was intended for use for addresses; it has been superseded by the ST_ADDRESS type.</value>
        </value-table></p>
    </value>

    <value number='7' name='ST_ADDRESS'>
        <p>Format:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='SAF_ETHERNET' number='0'>The value is a 6 byte MAC address.</value>
                <value name='SAF_IP' number='1'>The value is a 4 byte IP address.</value>
                <value name='SAF_ECONET' number='2'>The value is a 2 byte (net.station) address.</value>
        </value-table></p>
        <p>Presentation:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='SAP_NORMAL' number='0'>There is only this presentation type.</value>
        </value-table></p>
    </value>

    <value number='7' name='ST_TIME'>
        <p>Format:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='STF_5BYTE' number='0'>The value is a standard 5 bytes format (8 bytes, top 3 bytes ignored), measured in centiseconds since 00:00 1st January 1900.</value>
                <value name='STF_CTIME' number='1'>The value is a C time() value, measured in seconds since 00:00 1st January 1970.</value>
                <value name='STF_MONOTONIC' number='2'>The value is a centisecond value, used by OS_ReadMonotonicTime, measured in seconds since the system started.</value>
        </value-table></p>
        <p>Presentation:</p>
        <p><value-table>
                <value name='STP_ABSOLUTE' number='0'>The values are absolute and should be presented as time values from their reference base.</value>
                <value name='STP_RELATIVE' number='1'>The values are relative to the current time, and the reference base should be ignored. For example, a value of 250 in format STF_MONOTONIC might be presented as '2.50 seconds'.</value>
        </value-table></p>
    </value>

</value-table>
</p>

</category>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Ensuring statistic atomicity">

<p>The supplier is required to perform each read request atomically.  This means
a gatherer can rely upon a read operation producing consistent statistics,
but it cannot be certain quite when in time these statistics apply to:  in
some cases, statistics are virtually always out of date by the time the
gatherer obtains and uses them.
</p>

<p>The simplistic approach to ensuring an atomic read operation is to perform
the entire action with interrupts disabled.  This, however, has an
undesirable effect on interrupt latency for suppliers with many or complex
statistics and is not recommended.
</p>

<p>The suggested method is a three buffer scheme.  One buffer holds the
accumulated statistics, the second holds the increments (deltas) being
generated "live", and the third is either entirely full of zero values, or
there is an active read operation in progress and it holds a previous set of
increments that are currently being added (merged) into the accumulated
values.
</p>

<p>Two pointers are maintained.  One for the "live" buffer and the other for the
"merge" buffer.  The operation that is necessary to perform atomically is the
swapping of these two pointer values.
</p>

<p>The overall structure suggested is as follows:
</p>

<p>
<extended-example type='pseudo'>
start thread of control (ie SWI)

    enter mutex (eg disable interrupts)

        temp := buffer pointer 1
        buffer pointer 1 := buffer pointer 2
        buffer pointer 2 := temp

    exit mutex (and ensure interrupts enabled)

    add values from buffer pointer 2 into the accumulated values

    zero the memory described by buffer pointer 2

end thread of control (ie SWI)
</extended-example>
</p>


<p>This maximises the usefulness of the non re-entrancy requirement and requires
ONLY the swapping of the buffer pointers to be performed atomically.  All
other operations can proceed with interrupts enabled.  This minimal critical
region is the prime motivation behind this scheme.
</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Handling dynamic statistics">
<p>
    Some applications of the statistic interface will require a single RISC OS
module to behave as multiple suppliers.  For example, a device driver module
that controls multiple interfaces might well wish to provide an overall set
of statistics, and then an instance of a set of statistics per interface
controlled.</p>

<p>A separate SWI number is required for each 'effective supplier'.
This is not normally a problem, as very few modules approach the limit of the
64 separate SWIs allocated.  Gatherers are expected to obtain SWI numbers
through the enumeration method supplied, and should be capable of handling
dynamic SWI number assignment.  For example, a device driver may choose SWIs
63, 62 and 61 for units 0, 1 and 2, respectively.  If a gatherer were to
attempt to 'cache' these SWI numbers across invocations of the device driver,
then it might not correctly cater for the addition or removal of interfaces.
</p>

</subsection>


</section>


<section title='Services'>
<service-definition name="StatisticEnumerate"
                    number="A1"
                    description="Enumerate providers of extended DCI statistics"
                    >
<entry>
<register-use number="0">Pointer to the head of the enumeration chain</register-use>
<register-use number="1">Reason code (&hex;A1)</register-use>
</entry>
<exit>
<register-use number="0">New pointer to the head of the enumeration chain containing all the statistic providers</register-use>
</exit>

<use>
<p>
This service call is used to enumerate the statistic providers which are currently
active. Each supplier should allocate a block in the RMA containing the
<reference type='category' name='Statistics Provider Structure'/> and
fill in the details of its provider. It should then update the
<variable>next</variable> pointer to point to the supplied head of the chain, and
return the new pointer in R1. It must not claim the service.
</p>

<p>
    Statistics gatherers will use this information to decide what to display, and call
    the supplied SWI number as appropriate. Initially the statistics provider will
    supply the pointer in R0 as 0 when the service is issued.
</p>
</use>
<related>
    <reference type='swi' name='StatisticsProvider_Statistics'/>
</related>
</service-definition>
</section>


<section title="SWI calls">
<swi-definition name='StatisticsProvider_Statistics'
                offset='0' offset-base='StatisticsProvider'
                description='Obtain statistics from a statistics provider'>
<entry>
    <register-use number='0'>SA_DESCRIBE (0) or SA_READ (1) depending on the operation required</register-use>
    <register-use number='1'>First statistic, inclusive</register-use>
    <register-use number='2'>Last statistic, inclusive</register-use>
    <register-use number='3'>First byte of buffer in memory</register-use>
    <register-use number='4'>Number of bytes in buffer</register-use>
</entry>
<exit>
    <register-use number='0-4' state='preserved'/>
    <register-use number='5'>Number of statistics processed</register-use>
    <register-use number='6'>Number of bytes of buffer used</register-use>
</exit>

<use>
<p>
    This SWI is used to obtain a description of the statistics provided
    by a supplier, or the actual values of those statitics. It is expected
    that it be called at least twice, once to read the descriptions of
    the statistics, and then future times to read the values of those
    statistics.
</p>

<p>
    When the operation requested is SA_DESCRIBE (0), the statistics buffer supplied in
    R1 should be filled with structures as described in <reference type='category' name='Statistic Description Structure'/>.
</p>

<p>
    When the operation requested is SA_READ (1), the statistics buffer supplied in
    R1 should be filled with the values corresponding to those that would be described
    if SA_DESCRIBE (0) had been requested. Each statistics has a length as defined by
    the <reference type='category' name='Statistic Description Structure'/>.
</p>

<p>
    If the buffer is filled before all statistics are written, the SWI should exit
    with as much data as would fit into the buffer written and appropriate values in
    R5 and R6 on exit. Statistics gatherers may recognise this condition and provide
    extended buffers.
</p>
</use>

<related>
    <reference type='service' name='StatisticEnumerate'/>
</related>

</swi-definition>
</section>

</chapter>


<!-- MetaData -->
<meta>
 <maintainer>
  <email name="Charles Ferguson" address="gerph@gerph.org" />
 </maintainer>
 <disclaimer>

<p>
Copyright (C) 1994 ANT Limited., PO BOX 300, Cambridge, England.
All rights reserved.<br/>
</p>

<p>
Redistribution and use in source code and executable binary forms are
permitted provided that: (1) source distributions retain this entire
copyright notice and comment, and (2) distributions including
executable binaries contain the following acknowledgement:
</p>

<p>
``This product includes software developed by ANT Limited and its
contributors.  Copyright (C) ANT Limited 1994.''
</p>

<p>
and also in the documentation and other materials provided with the
distribution and in all advertising materials mentioning features or
use of this software. Neither the name of ANT Limited nor the names of
its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived
from this software without specific prior written permission.
</p>

<p>
THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED ``AS IS'' AND WITHOUT ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED
WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
</p>

<p>
NOT INTENDED FOR USE IN LIFE CRITICAL APPLICATIONS.
</p>
 </disclaimer>

 <history>
  <revision number="1" date="23 Sep 1994" author="Borris">
    <change>Tried to get the basic ideas into a coherent document.</change>
  </revision>

  <revision number="2" date="25 Sep 1994" author="Borris">
    <change>Changed precise details of register updating on return from some of the swi operations.</change>
  </revision>

  <revision number="3" date="Oct 1994" author="Borris">
    <change>Listened to feedback from reviewers.</change>
    <change>Adjust underlying model and streamlined most aspects.</change>
    <change>Added details of suggested scheme for atomic sampling.</change>
    <change>This issue not widely distributed.</change>
  </revision>

  <revision number="4" date="7 Nov 1994" author="Borris">
    <change>Tided up and checked consistency with reference header file.</change>
    <change>Added correct service call number.</change>
    <change>Added comments about effective suppliers and dynamic SWI number possibilities.</change>
    <change>name_tag as being outstanding added.</change>
  </revision>

  <revision number="5" date="28 Apr 2003" author="Gerph">
    <change>Added ST_TIME and ST_ADDRESS types.</change>
  </revision>

  <revision number="6" date="08 Aug 2020" author="Gerph" title="Restructure as PRM-in-XML">
    <change>Exported from Impression, and converted to PRM-in-XML structured format.</change>
    <change>Restructured document to match PRM structure and style.</change>
    <change>Added note that the features field is not currently defined and should be 0.</change>
  </revision>

<!-- Currently Outstanding

<p>
The name_tag field of the statistic structure has not yet been defined.
This will eventually provide a link through to some text from an IHV/ISV
supplied data file. This will be resolved before production code is
issued.
</p>

-->

 </history>
</meta>

</riscos-prm>
